Yesterday we spent the whole day talking
about what these machines can do. Chips,
models, agents, companies. Today I want
to start somewhere else. Every year
something that used to be ours alone.
Ours meaning uh humanity alone moves to
the other side of the line. Writing,
diagnostics,
diagnosis, design, code, conversation.
And every time it happens, we do the
same thing. We say, "Well, that was
never the important part." Anyway, the
real thing that makes us human is over
here on the other side of the line. Um,
so the question that opens day two with
this distinguished group uh is is a
little different. what these what these
machines can do
uh is extraordinary
and um so I have three people who have
who who are very well uh positioned to
kind of weigh in on where we're going.
Vanessa um measures what AI can do can
actually do with the data at Stanford
HAI. uh Yunav um has spent decades
thinking about what machine intelligence
means and he also helped uh initiate
some of the the um the index that that I
think is going to be referenced here. Uh
and he's zooming in from uh or Google
meeting in from Israel. He's the only
speaker uh of the 120 panels that we're
having zooming in. But that's because we
really wanted to have your voice uh as a
founder helping to run um AI21
and uh and we wanted to weigh in uh have
you weigh in from Israel um different
time zone showing we're global uh and we
have uh Satish at Dell who sees what's
uh what happens when thousands of
companies um put this kind of mentality
to work. So let's start on that line and
where and see where where we are right
now. All right. Uh, Yav,
uh, was was part of the early effort
behind the AI index, which Vanessa's
team in HI published today. So, we have
two generations on the same project.
That's kind of cool. All right. What has
AI already crossed that you once thought
was uniquely human? Uh, and did we even
notice when it happened? Who wants to
take that first?
>> I'll I'll go for that. Um so the I think
that going back to about 2020 when uh
GPT3 was launched and that uh first uh
glimpse into how good some of this uh
language technology is. previously
writing and language was really an
understanding was really thought to be
such a human thing and and I think
everyone at that time when we saw what
GPT3 could do um was quite surprised
that's when at HAI um the institute for
human- centered AI we uh coined the term
foundation models we started a center
for research on foundation models um to
really
understand how that these uh models will
impact the world around
Yeah, I think the one we take it for
granted is uh I'd probably say trust. Um
I mean a lot of these things are very
highly uh you know computational engines
and we seem to trust the outcomes much
much more than you know we were 3 years
ago. So a lot of the outputs now when
when I see the stuff it's pretty close
to what's the real thing is. So I think
if anything has changed I think as a our
level of trust in some of the outcomes
are producing I think that's impressive.
>> Y do you want to weigh in?
>> Um
when we started the index uh uh it was
an offshoot of the AI 100 project a
decade ago. um those intuition that
things are happening at a fast pace and
we better track them uh on an ongoing
basis uh uh we we little do did we know
how fast the pace would be. So on the
one hand uh I'm constantly amazed by
what modern AI LM and systems build
around them could do. On the other hand,
um uh they uh it's a totally open
question whether what they do uh is in
some way mirrors human traits. Um I have
uh I had a um a a a freshman seminar I
used to give at Stanford called can
computers think can they feel? And I
would ask six questions. Can computers
think, understand, feel, be creative,
um be conscious, have free will? And
what's interesting is um first of all is
it was a an excuse to get the students
who haven't been corrupted yet to really
think freely about, you know, what
machines can do. But at the same time,
what is it what do these things mean in
the first place? And what does it mean
for us, for example, to have free will
or understand? understanding is
something that I've been thinking a lot
over the past two years and I have more
to say about it but u uh it's
interesting that even defining what does
it mean to understand something is a
pretty uh slippery kind of uh subject.
>> Great. So I have a ton of questions. Uh
we're just getting started. So Vanessa
um the the AI index that you oversee
where you you're tracking a number of
things. you're using data to kind of um
compare things year-over-year. Where's
the g biggest gap between what people
believe AI can do and what the evidence
actually says AI can do?
>> Yeah. So, there's a concept that we
highlight in the AI index called the
jagged frontier, which is where the same
AI system can be very very good at one
task and very very bad at another. So um
for example while the NAI model this
past year passed or got a gold medal on
the international math olympiate a
competition that generally humans
compete in around math. Um it also
cannot tell time on analog clocks very
well. Um in the AI index we track uh
many many different benchmarks. Um
they've evolved over time. Um but this
idea of yeah the systems are very good
at one thing and not good at another um
is quite stark. Another example is
coding and agents. In the past year we
saw um these AI systems beat many of of
the benchmarks um testing agents. Um at
the same time in robotics there was a
new robotics benchmark that was released
this year called behavior that measured
how well robots perform on uh everyday
common household tasks. and it got a a
12% on that benchmark. So, the real
world is still quite messy.
>> So, Yuave, you're kind of like a Yoda
type character in the AI world. I I I
mean that as a compliment. Um, what's
happening now that generally surprises
you and what's happening that everyone
else finds extraordinary that you think
we're overreacting to?
Um
I think the um the thing that uh I think
we are guilty in AI of using illdefined
and uh imprecise terms and building
mountains around them. Uh AGI is not a
thing. It never was, never will be. It's
not intelligence is not one thing and
it's a it's a total total red herring.
Um I uh so I think the total
overreaction to that uh I think there is
um
um probably um uh the the thing that
this is wearing more practical hat. The
thing that I think people don't realize
is the gap between experimentation
and deployment in the enterprise.
uh and I think my my colleagues on the
panel can probably speak uh to this uh
more but uh there's a ton of
experimentation and discussion in the
boardrooms and in earning cold and so on
uh and there are some deployments but
because of as Vanessa said the jagged
intelligence the unpredictability it's
there are many applications which being
brilliant 95% of the time but not just a
little wrong but to total garbage 5% of
the time is a nonstarter and I think
people by and large underappreciate this
gap that exists. Well put, Satish. Um,
you're part of the tech 50. You know,
Dell is a major player. Uh, a lot of
tech companies are not AI native.
They're having to figure out how to be,
uh, how AI is a competitive advantage
versus a competitive disadvantage. What
are companies actually deploying versus
what they are announcing and how big is
that gap?
>> Um, the gap to your point is there, but
I think it's kind of narrowing quite a
bit. Um and you know as part of my role
you know one is I we I have a front seat
into what how we are actually leveraging
AI within Dell to drive a lot of
transformations. Um I also talked to a
lot of our customers uh mostly fortune
50 fortune 100 customers. Um it's
definitely accelerating in terms of
where we can you know leverage AI within
both within the corporate but I think
the the biggest thing is you know there
used to be times when companies used to
basically you know f nobody's fine
tuning anymore right companies used to
basically validate the models look at
accuracy so I think the models are so
good right now the one thing is the
there was a time where everybody was
waiting for the latest I think that's
gone so like you know we use whole bunch
of frontier models and n minus one
minus2 models indel a lot of those N
minus2 models are actually good enough.
So I think companies are trying to
figure out exactly what's important for
them, what kind of workflows are
actually going to make it really, you
know, what's important for their
business and starting to apply them. We
do the same thing Intel um and I think
that shift is already happening. uh and
every customer conversation I have uh
interestingly right um we we we you know
we are again we have AI products right
we are big in compute and storage and
that's Dell uh we are in the we are an
infrastructure player but increasingly I
would say a lot of my customer
conversations when I have they actually
ask me about okay what are you doing
about AI within Dell as an enterprise so
my conversation is not really not about
the products my conversation is about
what we are doing and how we are
transforming Dell and I think you know
um applying it to the major workflows
and stuff has been impressive. I think
the gap is absolutely closing.
>> Great. I I have a bunch of interesting
questions that I'm going to throw out
there. Feel free to pass if you don't
want to go on the record. You know, we
are recording this. Um is there
something we should never let machines
do even when they can do it better than
we can? And who gets to decide? And you
know, we have three different
perspectives on this. Who wants to kind
of weigh in on that?
So I'll make one comment. I think that
the what we need to consider is what
happens to the humans when we give that
power over to the AI and before doing so
need to think holistically about that.
So for example um in education
if AI can teach very very very well a
particular concept what are we then what
are the humans then missing out on and
when we learn we're learning also how to
work with other people social skills all
these different things at Stanford a lot
of the faculty are talking about how
students aren't coming to office hours
anymore so what is that what is it doing
to kind of the peripheral things that we
didn't quite think about when we're
deploying AI. Um, and is that kind of
the unintended consequences that we want
to have?
>> So you guys, is there something we
shouldn't let machines do?
>> Um, I would say at the end of the day,
accountability,
um, you know, machines can do the work,
but I think as humans, we are still
accountable for the outcomes. Israel. I
mean, you know,
>> um I think that
to me the question is it's um I mean one
is tempted to speak about you know uh
they shouldn't be able to allow to take
human life. They shouldn't be able to
just intermediate persontoperson
communication. I believe all of that. I
think and at the end of the day the
question isn't legislating it away but
really accounting for how machines and
humans coexist and how we re we humans
retain ownership control and
accountability. So I agree with Satish
on that. Yep. All right. If AI keeps
improving at the pace that it is, what
should we start teaching an
eight-year-old today and what should we
stop teaching? I mean, this is getting
really into, you know, like uh go going
up there uh about our species, but
8-year-old future 8-year-olds, next
generation 8-year-olds, now that we have
the symbiotic relationship with this
incredibly powerful technology, you
know, maybe it's an intelligence. Uh
Yoda said, "No way. Agi is not not what
we think it is." But but as we think of
the next generation, how do we prepare
them for this world that is moving so
fast? corporate
>> corporate um I would say be curious uh I
don't think that's uh anybody will
disagree uh critical thinking
um and if if you know lot of I would say
uh the people aspects uh we still need
to talk to each other
>> how many employees work at Dell today
>> um don't quote me on it I got to look at
the S3 probably somewhere around 80k
>> 80,000 so 8 years from now or 20 years
from now when the 8-year-old y old is
part of your workforce. Is your company
a fifth the size? Is it one person and
it's a virtual company? It's all AIS or
are you 10 times the size? Because those
eight-year-olds are going to be the
future leaders.
>> Do you have a do you have a strategy for
that?
>> You're going to get me in trouble now.
>> No, no. And feel free to pass. I just
But but these are things that I think I
mean
>> someone's planning for.
>> Yeah. The way I think about this is you
know I mean I'm a Gen X. So I started
during when internet boom was coming.
There are a lot of things which probably
you know I I was doing in core build
labs when I started a requirements
gathering and development work was
probably you know sitting in a committee
in a table going through this nobody
does this anymore so I I do think these
workloads are shifting and the way we do
things are shifting so I think my
8-year-old will figure it out but I
think to answer your question about D I
think look at the end of the day
corporations are transforming and I
think we are going higher order so
basically that you know if AI can do
some things then that you don't do that
work nobody's using typewriters anymore
right that's the way I I saw an
interview with David Solomon what like
maybe a couple months ago. Yeah. He was
telling you know remember what his
comment was. He basically said well look
when I started in Gulman you know
somebody will come and say okay you know
map this chart you know stock chart for
the last 3 years and it'll take six
analysts over half a day to chart plot
right today you can do that in 10
milliseconds that you're still there
right so he's like just our work work
shifts
>> he he went to my college and I knew him
because he was part of the alumni
meetings and I saw his career go like
this and the way careers are going to go
like this is going to be very different
with AI because people are going to get
an advantage because when they sleep
they're going to have 250 50,000 agents
working on their behalf and the whole
future of how people navigate their
their careers is going to change as a
result and AIs are going to be talking
to AIS and I think corporates need to
figure out that. All right. Um Yuav,
what do what do what do eighth graders
uh what are eight-year-olds what should
we be anticipating on on how to bring
eight-year-olds into the world?
I think um
uh a a job category that has always been
important but takes on extra importance
now is product management.
uh the uh interpolating between what the
technology can do and what the need is
uh is um is now super important given
how powerful the technology and super
hard given how complicate and opaque the
technology is. So I think the set of
skills that it takes to be a very good
technologyoriented
product manager is something that I
would in instill in people from very
early on and it has to do with
curiosity. It has to do with
understanding people product design but
also being versed in technology. So it's
not this threatening uh piece kind of uh
black box that you have no idea what
what it's doing.
>> Great. So this panel is a human
threshold. What's your take on you know
I think you have a 8-year-old or or a
little younger but you're probably
you're in the zone. You're thinking
about this stuff.
>> Yeah. Uh I have a
>> monosur and not let not letting the kid
touch the technology.
>> I mean I do think that young kids need
to learn how to work with each other.
Creativity I agree with. Um and so
yeah, nothing much to add. I I think
that also uh the the design element now
that we maybe not five and 8 year olds
but as they get older the design element
we can build many things. Now it's the
question of should you build it and why
should you build it?
>> Um is an AI a student in your Stanford
program and do you have a plan to take
AI as a student and and if you want to
pass or no comment uh as
>> not that I'm aware of. Okay, great. All
right. Is AI making us more capable or
simply making us more dependent? And how
would we know the difference? Who wants
to take that one? And I have a few more.
These are kind of just quick reactions,
human threshold type questions.
Well, I can chime in. Um, I think
technology has always been both. It's
made us more capable but uh in general
and less capable in specific things like
we don't do mental arithmetic as well as
we once did and we don't navigate uh uh
without technology as well as we once
did. uh but um uh the what we haven't
had so far every technology challenge us
more than you know than before and the
question I have I don't have the answer
is whether AI will continue to challenge
us intellectually in new ways or make us
lazy intellectually. I think that's a
big question for us and obviously these
days in connection with the math uh open
math problem being solved and
mathematicians ringing their hands about
this I think is a very important topic
for us as a society. Anyone want to
weigh in?
>> Uh I agree. I mean it absolutely is
making it more capable probably more
productive. Um you know I started
driving when there were basically AAA
maps you have to do you know you have to
know what exits. I don't think my kids
can drive anywhere today without a maps
you know Google maps. too. Um, is it
making him more dumb? No, I think he's
becoming more productive, leveraging,
you know, doing whatever he needs to do.
I I definitely think there is a
productivity aspect, but I also think
it's making us more intentional. I think
that's the part which probably we need
to improve on is like maybe, you know,
there are things which technology can
help do. So, it makes us, you know, much
more much more intent driven.
>> Great. Um, I have three more questions.
20 Did you want to weigh in on this one?
>> Yeah. 20 years from now, what is the one
thing you hope is still uniquely ours,
humans? Um,
you know, you guys are being more
philosophers on this, but uh
>> um Okay, I don't know if this is any I
hope that we can still do the things
that bring us joy. So, um whatever that
is, it's different for everybody, right?
Maybe it's helping other people. Maybe
it's hiking. Maybe it's um create doing
art, um music, all of these things. I
hope that those things that bring human
>> you don't hear a lot about is how AI can
unleash the creative and and I think uh
we're worried about AI taking jobs, but
maybe AI can be a multiplier of those
things and help help us create better
humans because you know a lot our
societyy's shifting so dramatically.
Yeah.
>> Before I go to the next question, either
of you want to weigh on that, weigh in
on that. 20 years from now,
>> I have a phrase that I thought I'd read
in the unbearable lightness of being,
but um I can't find it, so maybe I just
made it up. And it's that the hardest
thing is to know what to want. I think
when I think kind of uh something that I
would really hope that we hold on to as
humans, as people is taking ownership of
our aspirations and being very
deliberate intentionals about what are
we aiming for, what we optimizing for,
what we care about. That's a drop the
mic moment. Well put. All right, last uh
second to last question. Millions of
people are beginning to talk to AI. I
think Gen Z trusts chat bots more than
they trust doctors for medical. I don't
know if that's in your report and don't
quote me on that, but I I've heard that
a number of times, so it must be true.
Um, uh, not to, but as a companion,
confidant, tutor, or therapist, what
happens when machines become emotionally
important to us in a major way? Can a
relationship be meaningful if it's only
one side? If only one side is human. So
this is my second last question, but you
know weigh in on that. There's a human
threshold as we have this symbiotic
relationship with technology. What does
that imply?
>> So I'm no psychologist so I'm going to
divert my question to the trust thing.
Um we do have data in the AI index and I
mean this goes to like how different
people trust AI in different ways um
that around public opinion. So we
highlight surveys um from Pew that show
that
in the United States our trust of AI
that the trust that it will the benefits
outweigh the drawbacks is very low like
30 40%. Versus other places around the
world Taiwan, Malaysia, China that trust
in AI is much higher. And so it goes
back to some of the conversation we're
having is
there is a lot of opportunity with AI,
but if we don't trust it, then we cannot
see that opportunity. And um there are
concerns as well, but being able to see
both of those with eyes wide open and
figure out when and how to trust and do
the studies and the research to
understand what happens when people
trust AI like character AI more than
working with a human. Like what does
that mean? can help build that trust so
that we can deploy it in the right ways.
>> Either of you want to weigh on on that
before I ask my last question.
>> All right, I'll go to my last question.
My last question is what do you uniquely
know that no one else knows that you
haven't told anyone or you can't tell
anyone that in this intimate setting you
want to share? Uh, I mean, I think, you
know, AI was a technology.
Marvin Minsky was a neighbor of mine. I
went to his house. He's the one who
coined the term AI. I said, "Why'd you
come up with that term?" He said, "Well,
a bunch of us went up to Dartmouth um,
and we were talking about cybernetics
and we wanted to get a grant from the
government to give us money." And so he
said, "I coined the word AI. I could
have called it BI, but I thought AI
sounded scary and that they would give
me money for it." Uh so that's the
genesis of AI and it's artificial
intelligence but it's also really
augmented intelligence and and it's
taken on a life of its own but it's gone
back 75 years and it's just now that the
data sets are there or the
infrastructure of the internet's there
that we're seeing what people
intellectually knew was coming and it's
gone from a technology to now this is a
societal thing. What do you uniquely
know or what are you uniquely excited
about or or batshit scared about and
can't sleep at night that you have never
told anyone but you want to tell us now?
>> Well, I'll jump in just because I can't
let go of this mention of uh Marvin
Minsky coining the term AI because I've
always told that John McCarthy uh coined
the term.
>> Well, so the two of them ran that and
that was going to be my closer. the two
of them ran that that conference and
then John came here and founded the AI
lab at Stanford. So, it's fitting that
that this is a joint effort between our
labs. But yes, you're right. I agree. Um
they were both obviously giants. Um the
um so now I'll tell you what you don't
know. Uh and that's you've been thinking
about it all wrong. You're asking what
is the relation between us and AI, us
and machine.
But the truth is within uh not a very
long time
uh certainly within 50 years but maybe
10 uh the boundary between us and
machines will be uh totally uh
invisible.
whether it's because we speak with data
centers uh you know through our brains
or we have uh AI machines running
through our bloodstream speaking with
our uh with our nervous system um and so
the real question is who are we when
technology is just part of us and we are
part of technology and that's the part
that I find you know you know it'll
force us to ask you know what is free
will for example in this world and uh I
find it both fascinating and scary.
>> Yeah. Know 10 to the9 nanotechnology.
You just you know said the bloodstream.
Um you know I don't know if we're doing
justice to this topic but everyone in
this room and everyone in our society
should be asking these kind of
questions. Uh because we are going
through this metamorphosis and what does
that mean?
>> Um I'll give a non Yoda corporate
answer. uh uh you know a lot of
companies spend a lot of time in
validating the models trying to figure
out what to apply within their workflows
what workflows do you apply um I'll tell
you the latest and greatest frontier
models it doesn't matter you don't need
to have the latest and greatest uh you
know and a lot of people don't know is
most of our company del transmission we
use n minus one n minus2 models so what
we call is good enough a lot of models
are really good enough they have come a
long Okay. So, you don't need the latest
to actually go transform your company.
And if you want to talk to me offline,
I'm happy to do that. But that's what I
would say. Don't wait. You don't you
don't need the greatest. Right. So, like
somebody told me earlier, you don't need
a Ferrari to go grocery shopping. All
right. So,
>> you have the you have the last word,
Vanessa.
>> Stressful. Um, so I will set us up for
our next panel. Uh I think that we
should be all looking at the field of
science and how AI will be uh really
augmenting scientists and the
discoveries that we're able to have in
the next few years.
>> Great. And um Vanessa publishes this HAI
index which you all should uh track in
April. It comes out. They do like a road
show around the world kind of sharing
it. And I think it's needed more than
ever. And you know, thanks for your
leadership in helping to kick it off a
generation ago. uh and we love
collaborating with with Stanford and we
have a lot of MIT DNA uh but this is
really a societal issue and and today
human threshold kicking off today kind
of shows our values and we need to start
thinking about and I don't know if I
totally tapped into the sentiment of
this last week because I think there's
been a lot of talk uh but this is a
beginning of a journey that we're all
stakeholders in and we all can be
leaders and in Wall-E a bunch of people
that were couch potatoes just not really
active and I don't think that's the
future we want and I think we need to be
proactive and by having a corporate
perspective, a Yoda perspective and a
practitioner who's tracking all this
perspective shows that we got to
understand the different vectors that
we're on as we uh as we journey. So,
thank you. This is a kickoff 8:30 in the
morning. You're all here. Let's go.